<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Siva Thangeswaran]]></title><description><![CDATA[Siva Thangeswaran]]></description><link>https://sivathangeswaran.github.io/</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2020 04:52:18 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Full Stack Developer - not the end of the world]]></title><description><![CDATA[We all come across the buzz word “Full Stack Developer” often now a days in our industry (obviously Software Industry).  Like every single one who is on hiring side of the world is about “I want a full stack developer” and on the other side of the world, people are struggling to justify he/she is a full stack developer. I wonder what the heck is this and what we were doing all these years when we were hiring]]></description><link>https://sivathangeswaran.github.io//posts/full-stack-developer-not-the-end-of-the-world</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sivathangeswaran.github.io//posts/full-stack-developer-not-the-end-of-the-world</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;We all come across the buzz word “Full Stack Developer” often now a days in our industry (obviously Software Industry).  Like every single one who is on hiring side of the world is about “I want a full stack developer” and on the other side of the world, people are struggling to justify he/she is a full stack developer. I wonder what the heck is this and what we were doing all these years when we were hiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my world I never generalize my requirement on hiring with one line saying, “Full Stack Developer” and I always try to be more specific. Many times I also hear from my fellow developers that how I can become a full stack developer or am I a full stack developer or not. To my knowledge it is an unwanted questions we are asking our-self, without having a common understanding or an agreed upon definition of Full Stack developer.  Anyways leaving that aside, I just wanted to write my understanding of the term full stack developer and it is purely based on my perceptions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-is-a-full-stack-developer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#who-is-a-full-stack-developer&quot; aria-label=&quot;who is a full stack developer permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Who is a full stack developer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us agree that we are all software engineers and we will work for firms to develop and delivers software. A software engineer use multiple tools and technologies to develop a software and there is always a stack of technologies that helps to build the software. So if I answer like a one mark question then the answer is, a full stack developer is nothing but a developer knows all the technologies in the stack which helps to develop and maintain a deliverable software (smile)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So simple right? Yes, that’s it and we are only complicating and creating confusions. Again as you see, it is also little specific to the nature of the domain and the product what we develop. In my case we are developing and delivering a Web Platform to our clients so the technology stack here may be completely different from others like a Data Platform or a OS/Mobile platforms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s now dive into a specific stack based on a domain and a simple Web Application platform for a developer looks like, Front end, Web API and DB.  And now the big question arise, am I a full stack developer or why I should I look into DB, if I am a frontend developer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-explanation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#my-explanation&quot; aria-label=&quot;my explanation permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;My explanation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my explanation, imagine I am a doctor and working in a hospital. And I am a doctor because I have a MBBS degree, and I practice as a doctor to help patients getting out of their illness. Now if you see, there are also doctors who are specialized as Heart Surgeon, Psychiatrist, Cardiologist and etc. These specialists are experts in specific things and they can really do great job compared to others in that specific area. If you take a Heart Surgeon, he practice or do surgeries again and again as his daily job. So there are doctors and there are specialists, are these are two different people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, a Heart Surgeon is a super set of a MBBS doctor and he is still be able to treat simple illnesses like fever and flu any time. Coming back to the topic, we as a software engineer we all own a basic degree/eligibility (like MBBS) to be a developer and we all can develop software like a doctor treat flu (basics). (smile) That’s it, if I am a software engineer and I can develop software for a specific domain then I am a full stack developer and there is no special skill set needed for the same explicitly. But are you a specialist, is the key question here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, don’t scratch your head too much to be a full stack developer which you are naturally already. Just try to groom yourself to be an expert in one or more technologies which is very important as you grow up in your career and remember great software are built by experts not by full stack developers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/media/fullstack.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Design System for Enterprise]]></title><description><![CDATA[Design Systems is to provide products with a consistent look, streamline the design and development process, and boost team's productivity. And more than that, for an organization it gives a developer mobility between teams and products when all the Products in a company runs based on one single design system]]></description><link>https://sivathangeswaran.github.io//posts/design-system-for-enterprise</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sivathangeswaran.github.io//posts/design-system-for-enterprise</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;figure class=&quot;float-right&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/media/design1.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design Systems is to provide products with a consistent look, streamline the design and development process, and boost team’s productivity. And more than that, for an organization it gives a &lt;strong&gt;developer mobility&lt;/strong&gt; between teams and products when all the Products in a company runs based on one single design system. A design system is a combination of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A set of high-level design principles that clearly coalesce the design thinking and provide guidance for the proper use of those assets  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A collection of reusable digital assets (such as components, patterns, templates, icons, typographical hierarchies) that are generically defined enough so they can transcend their specificity within use for a specific application or project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that, there are lot of open-sourced Design Systems available to build your application on top of it and one such famous open source system from Shopify is &lt;strong&gt;Shopify Polaris&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://polaris.shopify.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). They even provide a React Component library to start with. Like the same in VMware, they built and spread the open source &lt;strong&gt;Clarity Design System&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://clarity.design/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;) throughout the organization, starting from a grassroots movement that expanded into a fundamental piece of nearly all applications and products. “It has changed the way we build and design products, increased the focus on design through the product development process, and even been adopted by other companies” - says Jeremy Wilken is a software engineer at VMware. Google’s Material Design is also one of the popularly used Design system on mobile space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design system to be a documented catalog of components and styles used within a product, including how and why each should be implemented. An enterprise software UX design system is not simply a style guide, as it includes layouts, interactions, and development; however, a product’s style guide would be included as part of the design system. Creating a UX design system can be a lot of work, but it pays off throughout the lifespan of your product. With that emphasize on design system for an organization, I listed few key consideration on building the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;essentials-in-effective-enterprise-design-system&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#essentials-in-effective-enterprise-design-system&quot; aria-label=&quot;essentials in effective enterprise design system permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Essentials in effective enterprise Design System&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand your broad organization&lt;/strong&gt;
Before even thinking about how an individual component could work within your design system, you need to understand the entire scope of the application. Look at every page, every state, every component — how are things implemented today? What’s consistent today, and what’s not? Your enterprise software UX design system should cover your application in its entirety, even those terrifyingly outdated legacy pages nobody’s touched in years. Understanding how components currently work across the system will allow you to define patterns, where components are considerably similar, and outliers, those components that are necessarily unique from everything else. We typically create a pattern inventory from every component we find throughout the system, including currently inconsistent patterns, from which we start analyzing which should be merged and which should be unique in the new system
&lt;strong&gt;Build for the system’s users (end user)&lt;/strong&gt;
While the designs within the system should all be focused on your application’s end users, the enterprise software design system itself should be built for the system’s users. Typically this means developers and designers, as well as potentially product and marketing. A beautiful, well-defined system is useless if not properly implemented — and implementation relies on more than just the creators of the design system
&lt;strong&gt;Design for longevity&lt;/strong&gt;
A good enterprise software design system should provide an effective framework for both current and future needs. As good view on the road map of the company and a foreseen technology changes, and end user advancement should be considered to ensure certain level of longevity of your system&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding-the-terms&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#understanding-the-terms&quot; aria-label=&quot;understanding the terms permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Understanding the terms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STYLE GUIDE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;: Designing Visual Style of Components&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mainly documents Colors, Typography, Icons, Logos and Branding Guidelines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Owned by UX team (&lt;em&gt;in collaboration with business&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PATTERN LIBRARY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;: Designing Visual and &lt;strong&gt;interactive&lt;/strong&gt; aspects of Components. Enables standardization and minimize code discrepancies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Along with Style guide, it provides templates, layouts and working components with code snippets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Owned by UX team along with Dev&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DESIGN SYSTEM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;: Builds a foundation for new Products and targets to provide consistent User experience across the organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Along with the capabilities of Pattern library delivers working component library&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Owned by entire organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;applications-vs-components&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#applications-vs-components&quot; aria-label=&quot;applications vs components permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Applications Vs Components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Design System consists of UI components and a clearly defined visual style, released as both code implementations and design artifacts. In the last few years, a consensus has emerged in the world of web development. Indeed, most JavaScript frameworks are largely based on &lt;strong&gt;components&lt;/strong&gt;. Components offer many advantages such as logic re-usability, centralized style and easy testing. As we talk about components in large scale it is also important to understand the Application scope better. The modern design system …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;component-library-as-web-components&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#component-library-as-web-components&quot; aria-label=&quot;component library as web components permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Component Library as Web Components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;enterprise-success-stories&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#enterprise-success-stories&quot; aria-label=&quot;enterprise success stories permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Enterprise Success Stories&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-stencil&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-stencil&quot; aria-label=&quot;why stencil permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why Stencil&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stencil is a tool chain for building reusable, scalable Design Systems. Generate small, blazing fast, and 100% standards based Web Components that run in every browser&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#conclusion&quot; aria-label=&quot;conclusion permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating a design system with stencil and react
&lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/fvaldes33/creating-a-design-system-with-stencil-and-react-2nmj&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://dev.to/fvaldes33/creating-a-design-system-with-stencil-and-react-2nmj&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building design systems for organizations - How to structure individuals and manage
&lt;a href=&quot;https://uxdesign.cc/building-design-systems-and-design-culture-3a7d07ae6b52&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://uxdesign.cc/building-design-systems-and-design-culture-3a7d07ae6b52&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Giving up on Containers over Serverless]]></title><description><![CDATA[Topics for today is, whether you choose to build and host on Containers or would you like to build it as a serverless application. When you talk about traditional vs Serverless then serverless is a clear winner in modern development, and I feel Containers are somewhere in between. Simon Wardley says, “Containers won the battle, but will lose the war to serverless”]]></description><link>https://sivathangeswaran.github.io//posts/giving-up-on-containers-over-serverless</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sivathangeswaran.github.io//posts/giving-up-on-containers-over-serverless</guid><pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The growth of Serverless ecosystem in recent times is tremendous, with respect to the features, support, monitoring and etc. This article is purely based on my experience and readings with respect to Web Applications. As of today, many traditional applications struggling to modernize themselves and on the other side many of the new applications are built on microservice architecture and they been deployed in containers by default (again emphasizing on Web Applications). Topics for today is, whether you choose to build and host on Containers or would you like to build it as a serverless application. When you talk about traditional vs Serverless then serverless is a clear winner in modern development, and I feel Containers are somewhere in between&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Containers won the battle, but will lose the war to serverless” — Simon Wardley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saying that, now straight away jump into the discussion points&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is Serverless Application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Architecting Modern Applications (JAM Stack, MongoDB Stitch)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Containers vs. Serverless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools and references&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Serverless doesn’t mean that you don’t have servers, it is just means that you don’t need to worry about those servers” - John Papa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;serverless-applications&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#serverless-applications&quot; aria-label=&quot;serverless applications permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Serverless Applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;float-right&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/media/serverless1.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Servers challenge us with additional cost, difficult to setup and a struggle to maintain. And that’s the simple reason why you look for serverless solutions, just keeping scaling and few others out. By the definition from AWS, Serverless is the native architecture of the cloud that enables you to shift more of your operational responsibilities to AWS, increasing your agility and innovation. Serverless allows you to build and run applications and services without thinking about servers. It eliminates infrastructure management tasks such as server or cluster provisioning, patching, operating system maintenance, and capacity provisioning. You can build them for nearly any type of application or backend service, and everything required to run and scale your application with high availability is handled for you. Serverless enables you to build modern applications with increased agility and lower total cost of ownership. Building serverless applications means that your developers can focus on their core product instead of worrying about managing and operating servers or runtimes, either in the cloud or on-premises. This reduced overhead lets developers reclaim time and energy that can be spent on developing great products which scale and that are reliable&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In relevance to this blog, most of us today write serverless code in conjunction with code written in traditional server style, such as microservices. For example, part of a web application could be written as microservices and another part could be written as serverless code. Alternatively, an application could be written that uses no provisioned servers at all, being completely serverless and I believe that is going to be the future&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were few challenges which was stopping us in the past from moving to Serverless are now getting resolved one after other. As an example, Azure functions comes with a great tooling support which helps developers to develop and debug serverless functions locally without any struggle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-jamstack&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-jamstack&quot; aria-label=&quot;the jamstack permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The JAMstack&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pure Serverless architectures are application designs that incorporate third-party “Backend as a Service” (&lt;strong&gt;BaaS&lt;/strong&gt;) services, and that include custom code run in managed, ephemeral containers on a “Functions as a Service” (&lt;strong&gt;FaaS&lt;/strong&gt;) platform. But here in this blog we are skipping the backend part little and there are more providers for BaaS today and they are always easy to plugin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those not familiar with the term, JAM means &lt;strong&gt;JavaScript&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;API’s&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Markup&lt;/strong&gt;. Translated into non-Acronym speech, means a client-side site where the initial HTML page is not web server like ASP.NET, or Ruby on Rails, or Express. This can be a little confusing, but you just have to understand the two purposes of web servers like ASP.NET. First they serve up assets (HTML, JavaScript, CSS, fonts, etc.) and second they reply to AJAX calls to store and retrieve data. This second function is what we do a lot of with our React and Angular etc. applications, and we mostly don’t think much about the first purpose. With the JAMstack we can still make those AJAX calls, but something like Netlify handles serving up our HTML, JavaScript, and CSS etc. And all those assets need to be static (which usually isn’t a problem)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very important to choose the correct architecture when you looking to build serverless applications. The JAMstack helps you to keep it simple and get it correct. The Stack emphasis a 100% server-side processes abstractions into microservice APIs. Using the JAMstack has huge benefits on performance, scalability, security, ease of deployment, and cost. I won’t really dig into details of all these, but just want to let you know that using platforms like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlify.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; along with JAMstack applications will ensures above mentioned benefits (a must read book on JAMstack - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlify.com/pdf/oreilly-modern-web-development-on-the-jamstack.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mongodb-atlas-offering&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#mongodb-atlas-offering&quot; aria-label=&quot;mongodb atlas offering permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;MongoDB Atlas offering&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 960px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/b93aaa8085f63a0b34d525b3006797c6/6d629/serverless2.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 51.640926640926644%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAKABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEDBAX/xAAUAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAB/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAHuNwDQQF//xAAaEAABBQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAAIQESEx/9oACAEBAAEFAr0yE3n/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAYEAACAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAIRMf/aAAgBAQAGPwKjXJf/xAAZEAADAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhEDH/2gAIAQEAAT8hFieLyKpwZzQw/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABCsD//EABYRAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQIf/aAAgBAwEBPxA1f//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAR/9oACAECAQE/EIf/xAAaEAEBAQEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAABEQAhMWFR/9oACAEBAAE/EAkZYKfHNXG06W5yjBQYzzeicP37mVVe7//Z&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/b93aaa8085f63a0b34d525b3006797c6/8ac56/serverless2.webp 240w,
/static/b93aaa8085f63a0b34d525b3006797c6/d3be9/serverless2.webp 480w,
/static/b93aaa8085f63a0b34d525b3006797c6/e46b2/serverless2.webp 960w,
/static/b93aaa8085f63a0b34d525b3006797c6/fcad6/serverless2.webp 1036w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/b93aaa8085f63a0b34d525b3006797c6/5a194/serverless2.jpg 240w,
/static/b93aaa8085f63a0b34d525b3006797c6/8a430/serverless2.jpg 480w,
/static/b93aaa8085f63a0b34d525b3006797c6/0781d/serverless2.jpg 960w,
/static/b93aaa8085f63a0b34d525b3006797c6/6d629/serverless2.jpg 1036w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;img
          class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
          src=&quot;/static/b93aaa8085f63a0b34d525b3006797c6/0781d/serverless2.jpg&quot;
          alt=&quot;serverless2.jpg&quot;
          title=&quot;serverless2.jpg&quot;
          loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
          style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        /&gt;
      &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, one of the commonly used DB Service Provider (DBaaS) is &lt;strong&gt;MongoDB Atlas&lt;/strong&gt; platform. The DBaaS platform Atlas also provide ability to build serverless applications. As you see in the screen grab you can build APIs using serverless functions available with MongoDB Stitch and hook them with the Atlas Cluster backend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stitch functions runs as simple JavaScript (ES6) functions in Stitch’s serverless environment and serves applications with Server-side logic, or enable Data as a Service with custom APIs. Serverless platforms on top of MongoDB helps reducing time to market, operational cost and development cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short Stitch functions can be invoked through HTTP endpoints or through external services like AWS API gateway. The collection of functions can be grouped through a Stitch App and the same can be hooked up with an authentication provider (a third party provider like gitHub, Google or Facebook, or we can implement a custom authentication)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;containers-vs-serverless&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#containers-vs-serverless&quot; aria-label=&quot;containers vs serverless permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Containers vs. Serverless&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS offers computing services in the form of IaaS with its famous EC2 container service, FaaS in the form of its serverless Lambda functions, and CaaS with its newly-released Fargate product. Among these three computing services to choose from within the AWS cloud environment, where EC2 has the most operational burden, AWS Lambda has the least, and AWS Fargate is somewhat in the middle on the spectrum. Fargate is a type of ECS (Elastic Container Service) where is takes little bit of Infrastructure burdens as you don not need to manage any EC2 instances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a container-based architecture, the number of containers deployed is determined by the developer in advance. In contrast, in a serverless architecture, the backend inherently and automatically scales to meet demand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Containers are constantly running, and therefore cloud providers have to charge for the server space even if no one is using the application at the time. There are no continued expenses in a serverless architecture because application code does not run unless it is called. Instead, developers are only charged for the server capacity that their application does in fact use&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Couple of key cons of Serverless are Cold Start and Vendor lock-in, but there are modern tools and frameworks can help you to overcome these problems. Example Serverless (&lt;a href=&quot;https://serverless.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://spring.io/blog/2017/07/05/introducing-spring-cloud-function&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Spring Cloud Functions&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Pivotal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#conclusion&quot; aria-label=&quot;conclusion permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lambda functions could be considered a more viable option, but they have their limitations. In the case of AWS Lambda some of these limitations include a 512MB ephemeral disk space limitation and 50MB deployment package size among, and a few &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/limits.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;others&lt;/a&gt;. Given all that, you no longer have to worry about provisioning your containers and defining scaling rules, you would still have to &lt;strong&gt;worry about such limitations&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is always been told in the past that Serverless is a great choice for an Internet of Things (IoT) and can help us performing little tasks based on a trigger. And also it is perceived like, Serverless is ideal when development speed and cost minimization is paramount and if you don’t want to manage scaling concerns. But given the background above on modern Web Application Development techniques like JAMstack and the growing initiatives like &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloudstate.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;CloudState&lt;/a&gt;, makes it highly possible to use Serverless as your platform to build large scale web applications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#reference&quot; aria-label=&quot;reference permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/premiumsupport/knowledge-center/cloudfront-serve-static-website/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://aws.amazon.com/premiumsupport/knowledge-center/cloudfront-serve-static-website/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.okta.com/blog/2019/03/21/build-secure-microservices-with-aspnet-core&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://developer.okta.com/blog/2019/03/21/build-secure-microservices-with-aspnet-core&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dzone.com/articles/squeeze-aws-lambda-for-everything-its-worth&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://dzone.com/articles/squeeze-aws-lambda-for-everything-its-worth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WBEzGFpAnhY&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WBEzGFpAnhY&lt;/a&gt; (Data API with MongoDB Stitch)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thundra.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://www.thundra.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudflare.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://www.cloudflare.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Web Components - a Big Step Forward]]></title><description><![CDATA[The key challenges for an organizations is building UI components with high re-usability, which also ensures brand consistency and avoid redundancy between teams. There will be number of teams in an organization which runs with different frameworks and technologies and which is naturally unavoidable. But if you can manage to avoid rebuilding similar components at a certain level, then that is a big achievement]]></description><link>https://sivathangeswaran.github.io//posts/web-components-a-big-step-forward</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sivathangeswaran.github.io//posts/web-components-a-big-step-forward</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-to-web-components&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#introduction-to-web-components&quot; aria-label=&quot;introduction to web components permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Introduction to Web Components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;float-right&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/media/wc1.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web components are nothing but a new set of web standards around HTML and DOM specs, which let the developers to &lt;strong&gt;extend&lt;/strong&gt; HTML elements  as new Custom Elements. This encapsulated custom element can be a simple ”&lt;strong&gt;button&lt;/strong&gt;” or it can be a complete Web Page and it is really depends on the requirement. Web component standards are supported in all modern browsers and polyfills are available for most of the old browsers. To explain conceptually, we all traditionally worked with server-side pages and built hundreds of Web Controls (e.g. Custom Controls in ASP.NET) which intern contributes to a huge spread of component library owned by an organization. If you toggle the same concept to HTML and client-side programming then that is nothing but a web component and component library. We will not go into the technical details of web components and for more read please follow this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webcomponents.org/introduction&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on the other side, we will also talk about the major frameworks like Angular and React, with more focus on &lt;strong&gt;Web Components&lt;/strong&gt;. Today, the growing demands on organizations to support multiple devices, requires lots of investments on resources, frameworks and technologies. As the given modern browsers and growing demand on code re-usability, it is time to shift the focus towards web components which is completely framework agnostic and purely on HTML standards. The objective of this blog is to share more insights to web components and also to highlight few organizational opportunities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-web-components&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-web-components&quot; aria-label=&quot;why web components permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why Web Components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key challenges for an organizations is building UI components with high re-usability, which also ensures brand consistency and avoid redundancy between teams. There will be number of teams in an organization which runs with different frameworks and technologies and it is naturally unavoidable. But if you can manage to avoid rebuilding similar components at a certain level, then it is a big achievement for any organization. The same can be achieved by introducing distributed web component libraries at organization level. We will cover more on organizational opportunities in below sections, but lets start with few key benefits,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 960px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/621f0fd86c8903c1e95e5549213c4542/f5b1e/wc2.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 40.61650045330915%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAIABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFQABAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAX/xAAUAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAB/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAG8ABf/xAAUEAEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEBAAEFAn//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAUEAEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEBAAY/An//xAAXEAADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARAx/9oACAEBAAE/IYsP/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABAMD//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8QP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8QP//EABkQAAMBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABMRFhgf/aAAgBAQABPxBKPpk8NUj/2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/621f0fd86c8903c1e95e5549213c4542/8ac56/wc2.webp 240w,
/static/621f0fd86c8903c1e95e5549213c4542/d3be9/wc2.webp 480w,
/static/621f0fd86c8903c1e95e5549213c4542/e46b2/wc2.webp 960w,
/static/621f0fd86c8903c1e95e5549213c4542/33ecb/wc2.webp 1103w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/621f0fd86c8903c1e95e5549213c4542/5a194/wc2.jpg 240w,
/static/621f0fd86c8903c1e95e5549213c4542/8a430/wc2.jpg 480w,
/static/621f0fd86c8903c1e95e5549213c4542/0781d/wc2.jpg 960w,
/static/621f0fd86c8903c1e95e5549213c4542/f5b1e/wc2.jpg 1103w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;img
          class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
          src=&quot;/static/621f0fd86c8903c1e95e5549213c4542/0781d/wc2.jpg&quot;
          alt=&quot;wc2.jpg&quot;
          title=&quot;wc2.jpg&quot;
          loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
          style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        /&gt;
      &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Browser Standards:&lt;/strong&gt; Web components is a standard that was added by the “World Wide Web Consortium” or W3C. The W3C sets or defines the standard of features that browsers can implement. Saying that, we do not need any complex framework to facilitate creation or rendering of components. The core elements of Web Components are Custom Element, Shadow DOM and HTML Templates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modularized Code:&lt;/strong&gt; Web components enable developers to write applications in a more modular way by breaking the applications down into smaller logical chunks with reusable functionality&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brand Consistency:&lt;/strong&gt; Having your front-end application code split up into component libraries or even design systems can ensure brand consistency across the company. It also provides an additional benefit of the ability to be used by all teams, regardless of tech stack. Web components are also extremely useful for teams who are working on many different projects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Browser Support:&lt;/strong&gt; As mentioned, all the modern browsers do support web components other than IE Edge. But we do have polyfills available to support the same. On the other side, we also hear initiatives from Microsoft to build IE with Chromium, which means that IE will naturally support all what Chrome as a browser supports. Also if your application is currently running with AngularJS or React like most of the teams today then you can easily integrate web components, you can find more details of the same &lt;a href=&quot;https://custom-elements-everywhere.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://custom-elements-everywhere.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serve Side Rendering:&lt;/strong&gt; As we build native elements, the complex html for an business requirement with data can be built in the server and rendered in the client rather building the HTML in the client. In certain business cases, this will give a high performance benefits e.g. content management systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-components-and-architectural-benefits&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#web-components-and-architectural-benefits&quot; aria-label=&quot;web components and architectural benefits permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Web Components and Architectural benefits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 842px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/8812699f9768e13d567f2ca2df9d6297/ce53a/wc3.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 57.95724465558194%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAMABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwABAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQACBf/EABUBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAB/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAHsIpqZf//EABkQAAIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQAAIRIf/aAAgBAQABBQJCYFUc/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECH/2gAIAQMBAT8Bp//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAh/9oACAECAQE/AYf/xAAWEAEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABBACD/2gAIAQEABj8CZz//xAAcEAACAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhMUFRgdH/2gAIAQEAAT8hl8Fuw9b7PIhNzvIhQR//2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAEIAP/8QAFhEAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEBFR/9oACAEDAQE/EFQ//8QAFhEAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEBFR/9oACAECAQE/EFA//8QAHBAAAgICAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREAMSFhQVGx/9oACAEBAAE/EMT4OoRwrihCF3bQzEkUsGab9hcxYNsVAECAoT//2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/8812699f9768e13d567f2ca2df9d6297/8ac56/wc3.webp 240w,
/static/8812699f9768e13d567f2ca2df9d6297/d3be9/wc3.webp 480w,
/static/8812699f9768e13d567f2ca2df9d6297/6366e/wc3.webp 842w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 842px) 100vw, 842px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/8812699f9768e13d567f2ca2df9d6297/5a194/wc3.jpg 240w,
/static/8812699f9768e13d567f2ca2df9d6297/8a430/wc3.jpg 480w,
/static/8812699f9768e13d567f2ca2df9d6297/ce53a/wc3.jpg 842w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 842px) 100vw, 842px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;img
          class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
          src=&quot;/static/8812699f9768e13d567f2ca2df9d6297/ce53a/wc3.jpg&quot;
          alt=&quot;wc3.jpg&quot;
          title=&quot;wc3.jpg&quot;
          loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
          style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        /&gt;
      &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building an enterprise level architecture around web components is definitely a big opportunity for organizations. Often the modern single page applications (SPA) is large frontend monolith and uses the microservice architecture excluding frontend. The monolithic frontend application will grow over time, developed by a separate team and gets more difficult to maintain. All these are signs to divide the large frontend application to multiple micro frontend applications. So that each micro frontend application can be developed by separate team and they all integrate in the frontend for users&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today most of the enterprise applications are built as microservices, but the applications which are built as microservices to break away from the monolith model are still sticks to a frontend monolith in most of the cases. In general to break away from frontend monolith, a shell or container framework will be built and all the child applications will be delivered using that container. At the same time, one of the below options will be considered to wire-up the shell and child applications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple SPAs and hyperlink between SPAs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iframe multiple SPAs as a Single Application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web Components and just one Application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among above options, web components are the most efficient way in modern development which helps you to build each micro apps as web components. As each micro app is a web component they can naturally used as an single application without an Iframe or a shell container. Assume you are developing an application like Office365 online or Google Apps, where each components are like Outlook, Excel or Maps can be developed as separate web component and can be stitched with a shell. Though they are not done in that way today, for example Google Apps takes the option one, which is Multiple SPAs and hyperlinks. So it is completely depends on the requirements and application needs whether we choose to have web components are not&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;user-interface-as-a-service&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#user-interface-as-a-service&quot; aria-label=&quot;user interface as a service permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;User Interface as a Service&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 960px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/173270ccf996bb179bf4c03ebc65023b/6e8e2/wc4.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 41.93254329990884%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAIABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFgABAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEF/8QAFQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAH/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAd2EAf/EABUQAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABB/9oACAEBAAEFAkf/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAgEBPwFH/8QAFhAAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAx/9oACAEBAAY/AiL/xAAZEAACAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARExQSH/2gAIAQEAAT8hWaXwjHE0j//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQfD//xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAwEBPxBX/8QAFxEAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERUf/aAAgBAgEBPxBykYf/xAAaEAEBAAMBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAABEQAhYTFR/9oACAEBAAE/EFJkK7+YgEW+a13DW06Gf//Z&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/173270ccf996bb179bf4c03ebc65023b/8ac56/wc4.webp 240w,
/static/173270ccf996bb179bf4c03ebc65023b/d3be9/wc4.webp 480w,
/static/173270ccf996bb179bf4c03ebc65023b/e46b2/wc4.webp 960w,
/static/173270ccf996bb179bf4c03ebc65023b/cd932/wc4.webp 1097w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/173270ccf996bb179bf4c03ebc65023b/5a194/wc4.jpg 240w,
/static/173270ccf996bb179bf4c03ebc65023b/8a430/wc4.jpg 480w,
/static/173270ccf996bb179bf4c03ebc65023b/0781d/wc4.jpg 960w,
/static/173270ccf996bb179bf4c03ebc65023b/6e8e2/wc4.jpg 1097w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;img
          class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
          src=&quot;/static/173270ccf996bb179bf4c03ebc65023b/0781d/wc4.jpg&quot;
          alt=&quot;wc4.jpg&quot;
          title=&quot;wc4.jpg&quot;
          loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
          style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        /&gt;
      &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have the re-usable UI components, how we can distribute the components between teams is an important thing. Choosing the right distribution method is actually off from this topic of web components, but it is still worth to write about it for a completeness. In general, sharing of UI components happens with in an organization will happen through internal repositories as component libraries. As we have growing version dependencies and backward compatibility support expectations. Having an internal NPM repository of web components, is a best thing we can do and which comes along with versioning. The users can directly pull re-usable components from this repository than re-writing them in their own project repo. Nexus or the latest versions of TFS does support delivering NPM packages from the repositories directly. Other side, we can have a internal CDN deliver the component dependencies too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here “User Interface as a Service” is a coined term based on the modern trends. But the opportunity here is to build a web component library and host the same in an internal CDN, to deliver across teams. Saying that, I have also pictured how the components can developed using different tools and technologies, and distributed between teams for re-usability and consistency&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shared components through a library, can further be used to compose products, pages or a section in a products’s web page. This is completely based on the requirement and as mentioned earlier, it is a progressive application development model. Day one, we will not have all the required components to build a product. Also the other side all the existing products will not have any business case to replace all its pages as web components. So a partial replacement or a progressive addition of web components and encouraging teams with build once model will help organizations to achieve their long time goals. An example of partial replacement is, I assume almost all the products has an requirement to display set of news headlines and detail story of the selected headline and call it as a “NEWS COMPONENT”. This news component can be just built once, with required inputs are parameterised like news source (API) and filters etc. Then we can use the same news component across all products, which will gives us high re-usability and consistent branding with look and feel by nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other side, if we have a full spread of components in our component library after some time, then we can also build a whole product with this library. Please refer to the image below which explains how a web page will be constructed from a shared library of components. The components are served through an internal CDN and each components are developed with different business purpose and scoped along with version support (e.g. a Navigation bar can be created at organization level and shared across to maintain high brand consistency)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;javascript-frameworks-and-web-components-support&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#javascript-frameworks-and-web-components-support&quot; aria-label=&quot;javascript frameworks and web components support permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Javascript Frameworks and Web Components support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also one of other key challenge that organizations has is to support diverse technologies used across teams and the growing demand on adoption to new technologies. After you end up in a diverse technology spread across teams, the re-usability of code and components with in the organization is no more an option. The good news is that, you can still allow your teams to work on different technologies and framework of their choice and still achieve high degree of re-usability by building Web Components with preferred technology. For example if your team it running on Angular, the new feature Angular Elements (nothing but Custom Elements) can work seamlessly within your Angular application and also the same can be shared as Web Components with other teams which are running with different frameworks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets talk little bit more about it, yes we can develop native web components with Javascript. But it will be a tedious task, knowing the complexity of implementing all the required interfaces. Given a chance, we always prefer to use a high level language than writing in machine language though it is more powerful. Here it comes the modern frameworks which supports you to write sophisticated Web Components with ease. A mentioned above, Angular Elements is one of its kind which provides a compiler to translate Angular code to Javascript (to ES5 or ES6 native Web Component)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Angular, Dojo2 and Stencil (Ionic compiler) are some of those which provide tools to develop web components. The delivered web components then can be used in any framework or in VanillaJS depends on your needs. These tools are little different from PolymerJS, where Polymer traditionally build and deliver components based on web component Spec and the same can work with one of your existing web pages along with &lt;em&gt;polymer.js&lt;/em&gt;. Saying that, it is a kind off runtime integration. But on the other side like Stencil are, just development tools which can output a native web component and it is just a development time dependency&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing Web Components using VanillaJS is also an option, but as mentioned above it is not much productive. Not just that, what about the rich features which comes by default from most of the frameworks we have today. For e.g. Dependency Injection, Data binding, Async Rendering, State management and etc. Also the rich developer experience with Typescript and various bundling tools. We don’t want to re-build all these features by choosing to work with native components rather pick one of your favorite tool like Angular Elements and Stencil and I listed little more details around the same below,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Angular Elements&lt;/strong&gt; - As mentioned by Rob Wormald, Angular Team, &lt;em&gt;“Elements are, Angular Component on the inside, Standards on the outside”&lt;/em&gt;. Angular Elements is a library along with Angular (6+) to support development of Custom Elements along with Angular Application development. As you all know most teams runs with Angular today and they can easily convert or develop their Angular Components to Angular Elements (nothing but web components) and which can seamlessly work with their own application and also can be shared to other team (non-angular) as web components (just a post build event can do the trick). More read - &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.nrwl.io/5-reasons-to-use-angular-elements-390c9a629f89&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;5 reasons to choose Angular Elements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dojo2&lt;/strong&gt; - One of the early player on Javascript frameworks (dojo) has come up with a full re-write called dojo2. As every other framework it is built on top of Component architecture, keeping high performance and re-usability as the objective. Dojo2 is an application framework and also provides a compiler for web components which can create really a small bundle (in few KBs) for each component.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stencil&lt;/strong&gt; - It is an Ionic team developed open-source compiler for web components with rich application features. Stencil adopts the best practice from Angular and React etc. For an example, it uses Typescript and on the other hand it supports JSX. Ionic 4 is built on Stencil, which comes with ready to use web components for your application development and Ionic is really a low code platform for mobile application development. Also outputs an optimized web component bundle and which can be added to any web application (&lt;a href=&quot;https://stenciljs.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;more read&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;angularjs-1-upgrade-opportunities&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#angularjs-1-upgrade-opportunities&quot; aria-label=&quot;angularjs 1 upgrade opportunities permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;AngularJS (1+) upgrade opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are number of applications built on AngularJS 1.x and running successfully. In some cases, they are also looking for an upgrade opportunity to Angular 2.x, for better performance and future enhancements. In the past there were lot of options discussed and suggested for upgrade from Google’s Angular team and others. Recent times in few Angular events there are topics discussed, we can use Angular Elements to upgrade AngularJS 1.x applications progressively. I did link a video of AngularConnect event which covers more about it (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aXOYa4S96OM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-success-stories&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#more-success-stories&quot; aria-label=&quot;more success stories permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;More success stories&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below I clipped some more stories around why web components are going to be one of the best things in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ionic 4&lt;/strong&gt; - Ionic is one of the most popular frontend UI library which comes with rich components and application features which can help you to build device compatible applications. The Ionic 4 (latest version) is now being shipped with web components. The key advantage of delivering web components is, you can use web components everywhere and they are supported i.e in all major modern web browsers. You can use Ionic 4 with any framework/language (TypeScript, JavaScript, Stencil, Angular, React, Vue or maybe jQuery. It’s your choice) to build hybrid mobile applications or alternatively build PWAs (Progressive Web Apps)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Typescript&lt;/strong&gt; - We can’t miss Typescript, when we are talking about frontend development. Typescript is continuously gaining adoption across the industry and also almost all the major frameworks are delivered in Typescript (e.g. Angular, Stencil and dojo2). Typescript is a super-set of Javascript and supports object oriented programming which helps finding issues in code much early in the development stage unlike Javascript. Also you can see the Typescript adoption trend &lt;a href=&quot;https://trends.google.com/trends/explore?date=today%205-y&amp;#x26;q=TypeScript,CoffeeScript,%2Fm%2F0h52xr1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. And back to advocating on web components, Typescript plays a vital role on developing web components with above mentioned tools&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EA Sports, story of winning with Web Components&lt;/strong&gt; - EA, the famous sports and gaming company, which runs number of web applications with different teams owning and managing the same individually. But years back they have chosen Polymer and web components as their frontend strategy across the company. And after that, it is an enterprise learning and here is the full story on this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y1hFSuSHkRk&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;. In the video, the team actually explains how they progressively achieved component based architecture with their objectives listed below,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facilitate deep theming capabilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work with any language and any framework&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support micro-site architecture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deliver User interface as a service (UIasS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a good success story and assume it helps us to understand the importance of web components, also how web components can help any organization to consolidate and standardize frontend development in the modern era. And that is the conclusion of this blog too!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[RDBMS to MongoDB - Organizing for Success]]></title><description><![CDATA[A beginner level talk on MongoDB, MongoDB is a general purpose database which is fast and scalable, it is used for a variety of use cases and a popular open-source document-oriented database developed by MongoDB Inc. The most common use cases for MongoDB include Single View, Internet of Things, Mobile, Real-Time Analytics, Personalization, Catalog, and Content Management. With the addition of multi-document transactions, it is even easier for you to address a complete range of use cases with MongoDB]]></description><link>https://sivathangeswaran.github.io//posts/rdbms-to-mongodb-organizing-for-success</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sivathangeswaran.github.io//posts/rdbms-to-mongodb-organizing-for-success</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-mongodb&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-is-mongodb&quot; aria-label=&quot;what is mongodb permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What is MongoDB&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;float-right&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/media/mongo_1.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MongoDB is a &lt;strong&gt;general purpose database&lt;/strong&gt; which is fast and scalable, it is used for a variety of use cases and a popular open-source document-oriented database developed by MongoDB Inc. The most common use cases for MongoDB include Single View, Internet of Things, Mobile, Real-Time Analytics, Personalization, Catalog, and Content Management. With the addition of multi-document transactions, it is even easier for you to address a complete range of use cases with MongoDB&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-mongodb&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-mongodb&quot; aria-label=&quot;why mongodb permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why MongoDB&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MongoDB is built on a distributed systems architecture, rather than a monolithic, single node design. As a result, MongoDB offers out-of-the-box scale-out and data localization with automatic sharding, and replica sets to maintain always-on availability. Business logic is distributed across Client Applications and eliminates centralized need for Stored Procedures in the backend system. Saying that, special skilled resources on SQL based environment is not required any more and the same can be covered by the Application developers who are more close to the business. MongoDB also ensures,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High availability — Replication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High scalability – Sharding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamic — No rigid schema&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geospatial support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy Integration with BigData Hadoop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Powerful Document-based query language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-organizations-choose-mongodb&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-organizations-choose-mongodb&quot; aria-label=&quot;why organizations choose mongodb permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why Organizations choose MongoDB&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations choose MongoDB because it enables them to build applications faster, handle highly diverse data types, and manage applications more efficiently at scale. Development is simplified as MongoDB documents map naturally to modern, object-oriented programming languages. Using MongoDB removes the complex object-relational mapping (ORM) layer that translates objects in code to relational tables. MongoDB’s flexible data model also means that your database schema can evolve with business requirements&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As organizations are more on building their infrastructure over cloud the fact, MongoDB is built for the cloud. Its native scale-out architecture, enabled by ‘&lt;strong&gt;sharding&lt;/strong&gt;,’ aligns well with the horizontal scaling and agility afforded by cloud computing. MongoDB can also be scaled within and across multiple distributed data centers, providing new levels of availability and scalability which is previously unachievable with relational databases. As your deployments grow in terms of data volume and throughput, MongoDB scales easily with no downtime, and without changing your application. In contrast, to achieve scale with relational databases often requires significant, custom engineering work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-developer-choose-mongodb&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-developer-choose-mongodb&quot; aria-label=&quot;why developer choose mongodb permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why developer choose MongoDB&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From Rigid Tables to Flexible and Dynamic BSON Documents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Documents represent data in the same way that applications do. This makes it much simpler and faster for developers to model how data in the application will map to data stored in the database&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Documents make applications fast - with data for an entity stored in a single document, rather than spread across multiple relational tables, the database only needs to read and write to a single place. Having all the data for an object in one place also makes it easier for developers to understand and optimize query performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;benefits-over-rdbms&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#benefits-over-rdbms&quot; aria-label=&quot;benefits over rdbms permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Benefits over RDBMS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relational database has been the foundation of enterprise data management for over thirty years. But the way we build and run applications today, coupled with unrelenting growth in new data sources and user loads are pushing relational databases beyond their limits. This can inhibit business agility, limit scalability, and strain budgets, compelling more and more organizations to migrate to alternatives. The RDBMS optimizes data storage efficiency (as it was conceived at a time when storage was the most expensive component of the system. But the MongoDB’s document model is optimized for how the application accesses data (as performance, developer time, and speed to market are now more important than storage volumes)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Schema evaluation and impact on Schema design - In the world of SQL, the developers and DBA working on a new development project using a RDBMS must first start specifying the database schema before the code is written. MongoDB enables developers evolve the schema through an iterative and agile nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The out of the box benefit of NoSQL database over RDBMS is the full text search feature. MongoDB provides a specialized index for text search that uses advanced, language-specific linguistic rules for stemming, tokenization and stop words. Queries that use the text search index return documents in relevance order. Each collection may have at most one text index but it may include multiple fields&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;benefits-over-other-nosql-databases&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#benefits-over-other-nosql-databases&quot; aria-label=&quot;benefits over other nosql databases permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Benefits over other NoSQL Databases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi ACID transactions supported from 4.0 which is unique from other NoSQL databases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Aggregation framework is extensive to match almost all the SQL features which not most of the NoSQL gives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Native, idiomatic drivers are provided for 10+ languages – and the community has built dozen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BI connectors - MongoDB can be easily explored with industry-standard SQL-based BI and analytics platforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MongoDB Charts is a new tool that enables you to quickly and easily create and share visualizations of your MongoDB data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;considerations-when-migrating-from-rdbms-to-mongodb&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#considerations-when-migrating-from-rdbms-to-mongodb&quot; aria-label=&quot;considerations when migrating from rdbms to mongodb permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Considerations when migrating from RDBMS to MongoDB&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importance of &lt;strong&gt;de-normalizing data&lt;/strong&gt; - as the collections are normalized the number of joins when you query increases. One biggest benefit of MongDB over RDBMS is less number of reads from the disk/store. Means, reducing number of relational joins reduces the no of reads to the physical store exponentially and which intern provides a high performance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other side, there are examples where &lt;strong&gt;normalizing data&lt;/strong&gt; can be beneficial, especially when data from multiple sources needs to be blended for analysis – this can be done using the $lookup&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schema modeling considerations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applications data access pattern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life-cycle of data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Growth rate of documents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embedding vs Referencing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embedding used in 1:1 or 1:m relationship where many objects always used in the context of the parent document, or the other way there is not much relevance for the child document if the parent is deleted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Referencing is more of normalization m:1 or m:m relationships, if the objects are referenced from different sources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indexes&lt;/strong&gt; in MongoDB largely correspond to indexes in a relational database. MongoDB uses B-Tree indexes, and natively supports secondary indexes. As such, it will be immediately familiar to those coming from a SQL background&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-more-mongodb-offers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-more-mongodb-offers&quot; aria-label=&quot;what more mongodb offers permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What more MongoDB offers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than what is been discussed above, MongoDB as an enterprise offers lot of services and offerings which an organization or an individual can get benefited. I have listed them below for reference and will cover them in-detail in future&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MongoDB Atlas&lt;/strong&gt;: Database as a Service For MongoDB, this service, offered in the public cloud. Atlas enables customers to deploy, operate, and scale MongoDB databases on AWS, Azure, or GCP in just a few clicks or programmatic API calls. MongoDB Atlas is available through a pay-as-you-go model and billed on an hourly basis. It’s easy to get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MongoDB Stitch&lt;/strong&gt;: The MongoDB Stitch serverless platform facilitates application development with simple, secure access to data and services from the client – getting your apps to market faster while reducing operational costs. This provide four services, Stitch QueryAnywhere, Stitch Functions, Stitch Triggers and Stitch Mobile Sync.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MongoDB Mobile&lt;/strong&gt;: MongoDB Mobile lets you store data where you need it, from IoT, iOS, and Android mobile devices to your backend – using a single database and query language&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MongoDB Compass&lt;/strong&gt;: Tool which provides the ability to visualize explain plans, presenting key information on how a query performed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MongoDB Cloud Manager&lt;/strong&gt;: is a cloud-based tool that helps you manage MongoDB on your own infrastructure. With automated provisioning, fine-grained monitoring, and continuous backups, you get a full management suite that reduces operational overhead, while maintaining full control over your databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MongoDB Consulting&lt;/strong&gt;: MongoDB Consulting packages get you to production faster, help you tune performance in production, help you scale, and free you up to focus on your next release&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MongoDB Training&lt;/strong&gt;: MongoDB Training helps you become a MongoDB expert, from design to operating mission-critical systems at scale. Whether you’re a developer, DBA, or architect, we can make you better at MongoDB&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MongoDB Enterprise&lt;/strong&gt;: MongoDB Enterprise Advanced is the best way to run MongoDB in your data center. It’s a finely-tuned package of advanced software, support, certifications, and other services designed for the way you do business&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 900px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/f2df5a198e6840d6fa813cbf0174f68a/7288a/mongo2.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 56.22222222222223%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAALABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwAAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQFA//EABYBAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIAAf/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABd0kFtgWCv//EABkQAAIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECABESEP/aAAgBAQABBQJXuXwqLyAUAx//xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQEf/aAAgBAwEBPwGn/8QAFxEBAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEREv/aAAgBAgEBPwHEKf/EABgQAAIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABICFB/9oACAEBAAY/AnexR//EABoQAQACAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESExQVH/2gAIAQEAAT8hpWFiINlxbUbS9xwFmus7vXs//9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABBrD//EABYRAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAEf/aAAgBAwEBPxDcLf/EABYRAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAQf/aAAgBAgEBPxBTZA3/xAAdEAEAAgICAwAAAAAAAAAAAAABABEhQTFRYZGh/9oACAEBAAE/EGwT8s04+QxszMwePEUgSm+X3KjW67udxyIlCqmf/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/f2df5a198e6840d6fa813cbf0174f68a/8ac56/mongo2.webp 240w,
/static/f2df5a198e6840d6fa813cbf0174f68a/d3be9/mongo2.webp 480w,
/static/f2df5a198e6840d6fa813cbf0174f68a/131f1/mongo2.webp 900w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 900px) 100vw, 900px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/f2df5a198e6840d6fa813cbf0174f68a/5a194/mongo2.jpg 240w,
/static/f2df5a198e6840d6fa813cbf0174f68a/8a430/mongo2.jpg 480w,
/static/f2df5a198e6840d6fa813cbf0174f68a/7288a/mongo2.jpg 900w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 900px) 100vw, 900px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;img
          class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
          src=&quot;/static/f2df5a198e6840d6fa813cbf0174f68a/7288a/mongo2.jpg&quot;
          alt=&quot;mongo2.jpg&quot;
          title=&quot;mongo2.jpg&quot;
          loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
          style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        /&gt;
      &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>